Okay בוקר טוב *boker tov*, today's דף *daf* is we'll call it
ט"ו *tes vav*, but we're going to start on the middle of
י"ד עמוד ב *yud daled amud bet*, so 14B by אמר רבי
יהושע בן קרחה Rabbi Yehoshua ben Korcha, למה קדמה lama kadma, פרשת
שמע Shema, *Amar Rabi Yehoshua ben Korcha lama kadma parshat Shema?* So
we had just discussed yesterday the issue about בין הפרקים *bein haprakim*
and what the how you flow in from אני ה' אלהיכם אמת
*Ani Hashem Elokeichem Emet* and that's the importance of joining both of
those and and the interesting questions about how בין הפרקים *bein haprakim*
applies to things other than שמע Shema, *Shema*, how does it apply
to responding to parts of דבננ *davenen* like קדיש *Kaddish* during שמע
Shema *Shema* and so on. Now we move on to the statement
in the משנה Mishnah, *Mishnah* of רבי יהושע בן קרחה Rabbi Yehoshua
ben Korcha *Rabi Yehoshua ben Korcha* about the order of שמע Shema
*Shema*, והיה אם שמוע *V'haya im Shamoa*, and ציצית tzitzis. *Tzitzit*.
And let's also remember that yesterday we mentioned, last night we mentioned,
that the פרשת ציצית parshas tzitzis, *parshat Tzitzit*, at least in ארץ
ישראל *Eretz Yisrael*, was mostly skipped at night, either because the מצוה
mitzvah, *mitzvah* of ציצית tzitzis *Tzitzit* doesn't apply at night or maybe
there's the מצוה mitzvah, *mitzvah* of זכר יציאת מצרים *zecher yetziat Mitzrayim*
is not so clear if it applies at night. Anyway, so that
was interesting to note those different regional differences. But now we get
to the statement that what's the order? The order is: the first
פרשה parsha *parsha* of שמע Shema *Shema* is קבלת עול מלכות שמים
kabbalas ol malchus shamayim. *kabbalat ol malchut shamayim*, the second פרשה parsha
*parsha*, which is the fundamental, the foundation, then the second פרשה parsha
*parsha* right after שמע Shema ישראל ואהבת את ה' אלהיך *Shema Yisrael
V'ahavta et Hashem Elokecha*, the second פרשה *parsha* turns more to a
doesn't have the שמע Shema, ישראל ה' אלהינו ה' אחד *Shema Yisrael
Hashem Elokeinu Hashem Echad*, that foundation, but it turns more to the
practical and there's much more of an emphasis on the מצוות mitzvot.
*mitzvot*. And then the third one about the ציצית tzitzis *Tzitzit*, that's
just because as we said, you know, ציצית *tzitzit* themselves don't apply
at night, maybe the מצוה mitzvah *mitzvah* of זכר יציאת מצרים *zecher
yetziat Mitzrayim* doesn't apply at night, and therefore they're third. So let's
see what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says on this. אמר רבי יהושע
בן קרחה Rabbi Yehoshua ben Korcha. למה קדמה פרשת שמע Shema, *Amar
Rabi Yehoshua ben Korcha lama kadma parshat Shema?* תניא *Tanya*, we learned
in the בריתא *braita*, שמשון בן יוחאי אומר *Shimshon ben Yochai omer*,
בדין הוא שיקדים שמע Shema לוהיה אם שמוע *bidin hu sheyakdim Shema
l'Vahaya im Shamoa*. Now here's a different approach. It makes sense that
שמע Shema *Shema* comes before והיה אם שמוע *V'haya im Shamoa* in
the דבננ *davenen*, שזה ללמוד lilmod, וזה ללמד *she-ze lilmod v'ze lelamed*,
that שמע Shema, *Shema* is learning and והיה אם שמוע *V'haya im
Shamoa* is teaching. Now where is שמע Shema *Shema* learning? It says
ודברת בם *V'dibarta bam*, right? And as we pointed out the other
day and Chaim pointed out just right, that והיה אם שמוע *V'haya
im Shamoa* it says ושיננתם לבניך לדבר בם *v'shinantam l'vanecha ledaber bam*,
you teach your children so they might speak of them, but והיה
אם שמוע *V'haya im Shamoa* never explicitly tells you to learn, it
tells you to teach, not to learn. So here it's a different
order, not as you would a sort of a chronological order than
a conceptual order. First you have to learn and before you can
teach, then you teach. One second. והיה אם שמוע לויאמר *V'haya im
Shamoa l'Vayomer*, and then והיה אם שמוע *V'haya im Shamoa* comes before
the third פרשה *parsha*, שזה ללמד וזה לעשות *she-ze lelamed v'ze la'asot*,
that it should be ללמוד ללמד לשמור ולעשות *lilmod lelamed lishmor vela'asot*
is normally the phrase in חז"ל Chazal *Chazal*, you learn and you
teach and then you do. So there's the movement from talking about
it, whether for yourself or to others, and then translating it into
action. So that's a different type of a progression than the first,
the first which I would say more a little bit about the
foundations. In a way it's a little bit sometimes I tell people
the example that you look at the difference between the רמב"ם *Rambam*
and the שולחן ערוך *Shulchan Aruch*, how they begin, how, you know,
how their works are organized. So you know, the רמב"ם *Rambam* begins:
יסוד היסודות ועמוד החכמות *yesod hayesodot ve'amud hachachamot*, the first thing you
have to know is that God exists, and then he talks to
you all about the principles about God, then he moves into the
מצוות mitzvos, *mitzvot* that relate to loving of God, and then he
turns into sort of other practical things. A very sort of conceptual:
here's the foundation, you know, and here's what builds on it. You
open up the שולחן ערוך *Shulchan Aruch*, what's the first thing the
שולחן ערוך *Shulchan Aruch* tells you? Here's what you do when you
wake up in the morning, right? Very chronological. So which one do
you think people are going to use more anyway? שולחן ערוך *Shulchan
Aruch* is very user friendly. So anyway, that's a little bit of
this difference here, that the first one is קבלת עול מלכות שמים
kabbalas ol malchus shamayim, *kabbalat ol malchut shamayim*, קבלת מצוות mitzvos, *kabbalat
mitzvot*, and then, you know, and so on, the and שמע Shema
*Shema* and whatever the last פרשה *parsha* is sometimes here. No, progression.
You learn, you teach, you talk about them, you know them, and
that enables learning enables you to teach and learning and teaching the
knowledge enables you to then do. So it's a little bit more
of a progressive thing. Okay, fine. Alright, so now the גמרא Gemara,
*Gemara* says like this, okay, אטו שמע Shema. ללמוד אית ביה ללמד
ולעשות לית ביה *atu Shema lilmod it be lelamed vela'asot leit be?*
What do you mean? שמע Shema *Shema* has learning but it doesn't
have teaching and doing? והא כתיב ושיננתם *v'ha chtiv v'shinantam*, first it
says you shall teach them in שמע Shema. *Shema*, so that's teaching.
וקשרתם וכתבתם *uksherterm uchtavtam*, maybe it doesn't speak about generic מצוות mitzvos
*mitzvot* like והיה אם שמוע *V'haya im Shamoa*, but it does say
speak about some מצוות *mitzvot*, תפילין tfillin ומזוזה *Tefillin uMezuzah*. So there
it has all three. והיה אם שמוע ללמד אית ביה ולעשות לית
ביה *V'haya im Shamoa lelamed it be vela'asot leit be?* You're telling
me it doesn't have doing? והכתיב וקשרתם וכתבתם *v'hachtiv uksherterm uchtavtam*, it
has תפילין tfillin ומזוזה *Tefillin uMezuzah*. So what, ציצית *tzitzis* is ציצית
*tzitzis*, big deal. So והיה אם שמוע *V'haya im Shamoa* has תפילין
tfillin ומזוזה *Tefillin uMezuzah*. So what do you mean that it's like
this progression? אלא הכי קאמר *ela hachi ka'amar*, בדין הוא שיקדים שמע
Shema לוהיה אם שמוע *bidin hu sheyakdim Shema l'Vahaya im Shamoa*. So
now it's not like an order, it's like it's like more than
the other. This has all three of them. והיה אם שמוע לויאמר
*V'haya im Shamoa l'Vayomer*, והיה אם שמוע *V'haya im Shamoa* comes before
ויאמר *Vayomer*, שזה יש בה ללמד ולעשות *she-ze yesh bah lelamed vela'asot*,
that has teaching and doing it, so it has two out of
the three. And then והיה אם שמוע *V'haya im Shamoa*, ויאמר אין
בה אלא לעשות בלבד *Vayomer ein bah ela la'asot bilvad*, and ויאמר
*Vayomer* doesn't. and it doesn't discuss learning Torah, teaching Torah, it only
talks about the doing. So therefore it's more like three, two, and
one, but even with that you could still say that what is
different emphasizes a sense of progression. You know, so,
but it does point out that it's not like only one of
the three, it's three, two, and then one. Okay, now the גמרא
Gemara says like this: ותיפוק ליה מדרבי יהושע בן קרחה, v'teipok lei
mid'Rabbi Yehoshua ben Korcha, why did רבי שמעון בר יוחאי Rabbi Shimon
bar Yochai need this approach, what about רבי יהושע בן קרחה, Rabbi
Yehoshua ben Korcha. he has a nice approach about קבלת עול מלכות
שמים. kabbalas ol malchus shamayim, חדא ועוד קאמר, chada ve'od ka'amar, fine,
one good reason and another reason. חדא כדי שיקבל עול מלכות שמים
תחילה, chada k'dei sheyakabel ol malchus shamayim techila,
one is to start with קבלת עול מלכות שמים, Ol Malchut Shamayim
ואחר כך יקבל עול מצות, ve'achar kach yakabel ol mitzvos, and then
accepting מצות, mitzvos, and then if you would, and then the maybe
the doing מצות mitzvos or then the third פרשה just because it
has less, it doesn't apply as much at night. ועוד, ve'od, that's
one reason. Another approach is משום דאית בה הני מילי אחריתי mishum
d'is ba hani milei achriti that point you make: ללמוד וללמד ולעשות.
lilmod u'lelamed ve'la'asot. Okay,
fine. Now it does seem by the way the phrase למה קדמה,
the fact that we're coming up with different reasons is that the
liturgy was already fixed, right, the three פרשיות parshiyos of שמע, Shema.
and you know, and they are just reflecting after the fact why
did, you know, what was the reason it was organized this way.
So it's more like after, you know, what, it seems to be
more like a type of a speculation and therefore they're coming up
with different reasons. Why do you think חז"ל Chazal, put together the
דאווענינג davening this way? Of course they were חז"ל, but they were
at a later time presumably than the, you know, than it was
originally fixed, and they're speculating as to the order. Okay, so now
the גמרא Gemara continues the following: רב, Rav, now that we're talking
about this progression of ללמוד וללמד ולעשות, lilmod u'lelamed ve'la'asot, we're going
to have an interesting discussion about that in actual practice. רב משי
ידיה וקרא קריאת שמע ואנח תפילין. Rav mashi yadei ve'kara krias shema
ve'anach tfillin. רב Rav washed his hands, washing hands in the morning,
we're not going to discuss the full import about that right now.
Part of it is obviously there's an aspect that people, you know,
know about which is the whole sort of רוח רע, ruach ra,
but that's not the focus of the גמרא, Gemara it's more about
washing just so that they should be clean for דאווענינג, davening, you
know, and to prepare yourself for דאווענינג. davening. And then he would
say שמע, Shema and then he put on תפילין tfillin וצלי, ve'tzali,
and then he would דאווען daven שמונה עשרה. Shmoneh Esrei. So first
of all that's interesting, it leads תוספות Tosfos to a whole discussion
about if you get your תפילין tfillin and טלית tallis and תפילין
tfillin between שמע Shema and שמונה עשרה Shmoneh Esrei can you put
them on with a ברכה bracha or not. And תוספות Tosfos says,
first of all תוספות Tosfos says, well there's first of all more
of an importance of having your תפילין tfillin on for שמונה עשרה
Shmoneh Esrei than your טלית. tallis. That's a little funny because, and
I don't want to get into that because you know תפילין tfillin
we understand and the גמרא's Gemara going to get to this, the
idea of תפילין tfillin on before שמע Shema. and even טלית tallis
on before שמע Shema. because in the שמע Shema, you talk about
תפילין tfillin and then in the third פרשה you talk about ציצית.
So there's an idea don't be talking about it if you're not
doing it. But for the שמונה עשרה, Shmoneh Esrei, the גמרא Gemara
sometimes says there's an idea of course to be enwrapped with טלית
tallis and תפילין tfillin, when you're דאווענינג davening שמונה עשרה, Shmoneh Esrei,
the way it sort of puts you in a particular sort of
mode, but that there's greater weight for תפילין tfillin to טלית tallis
whatever is very unclear. Anyway, תוספות Tosfos does say look he is
doing it beforehand, but then he says it doesn't prove when you
make the ברכה. bracha. Maybe you put it on before, if you
get your טלית tallis or תפילין tfillin? before שמונה עשרה Shmoneh Esrei
after, you know, in the middle of שמע, Shema maybe you put
it on so it's on for שמונה עשרה, Shmoneh Esrei, but it
doesn't prove you can interrupt to make the ברכה, bracha, maybe you
make the ברכה bracha afterwards. So that's just
a, yeah, but you don't have a choice here because you can't
interrupt the שמע, Shema and you're still wearing טלית tallis and תפילין,
tfillin right, you're not done, you're still wearing them after שמונה עשרה,
Shmoneh Esrei, you're still doing the מצוה, mitzvah it's a long מצוה,
mitzvah so you'd still be making the ברכה bracha before, you know,
not after the מצוה's mitzvah complete but while you're still in the
middle of a ברכה. bracha.
Why didn't he put them on earlier?
He didn't have it, he couldn't find it, he didn't get it,
it wasn't the זמן, zman, it happens sometimes that you don't have
access to this.
Is this a one-time thing or is it something...
we'll talk in the גמרא Gemara whether in a רב Rav it
was a one-time thing. I am just giving you תוספות's Tosfos footnote
that תוספות Tosfos says what is this? He's putting on תפילין tfillin
between שמע Shema and שמונה עשרה, Shmoneh Esrei, did he make a
ברכה bracha on his תפילין? Tefillin So תוספות Tosfos says you see
A, it's important that if you get, if you didn't have access
to your תפילין Tefillin, and he had ציצית before שמונה עשרה Shmoneh
Esrei and you're in the middle of שמע Shema it's still important
enough to put it on now so you're wearing it for שמונה
עשרה. Shmoneh Esrei. And then there's a question can you make the
ברכה bracha now or do you wait to make the ברכה bracha
after.
Yes. Okay so let's keep on going. So all of that was
a footnote, but anyway, yes. What is the source for washing of
hands before דאווענינג? davening? Yeah this and a couple of things we're
going to be saying. Yes.
Okay,
so now so רב Rav washed his hands, said שמע, Shema and
then put on תפילין Tefillin and then דאווענד. davened. Okay, so let's
take a look what this is about. So it says like this:
והיכי עביד הכי, ve'heichi avid hachi, how How did he do that,
meaning basically put the תפילין Tefillin *Tefillin* on after the שמע Shema
*Shema*? That's going to be the focus here. דתניא de-tanya, *D'tanya* we
taught in the ברייתא Baraita, *Baraita*, חופר כוך למת *Chofair kukh l'meit*
if somebody is digging a sort of not a grave because this
was like inside of a cave, so a niche, right, like for
a corpse, בקבר *bakever*, פטור מקריאת שמע Shema ומן התפילה ומן התפילין
ומכל מצוות האמורות בתורה *patur mikrias shema u'min hatefillah u'min hatefillin u'mikol
mitzvos ha'amuros batorah*. You don't have to דאווענט *davened* and say שמע
Shema *shema*, תפילין Tefillin *tefillin*, don't have to do any מצוה mitzvah
*mitzvah*. עוסק במצוה פטור מן המצוה *Osek bemitzvah patur
min hamitzvah*. הגיע זמן קריאת שמע krias shema *Higia zman krias shema*,
now it's time for the שמע Shema. *shema*, so what do you
do? עולה olah ונוטל ידיו *Oleh venoteil yadav*, you get out of
the cave, you wash your hands, ומניח תפילין Tefillin *u'meniach tefillin*, you
put on תפילין Tefillin *tefillin*, וקורא קריאת שמע krias shema ומתפלל *vekore
krias shema umispaleil*, and you say שמע Shema *shema* and דאווען *daven*.
Now it makes no sense. הכל קשיא *Hakol kashya*, this contradicts itself.
רישא אמר פטור *Reisha amar patur*, you say you're פטור *patur* from
all these things, וסיפא חייב *vesayfa chayav*, and then you tell me
here's how you
do
all these things, here's how you do
שמע Shema, *shema*
and תפילה tfila *tefillah* and תפילין Tefillin *tefillin*. So גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
says okay, לא קשיא *lav kashya*, it's not difficult. סיפא בתרי ורישא
בחד *Sayfa bitrei ureisha bechad*. The beginning is meaning you're the only
guy around, so then you can't interrupt. Interrupt means the מצוה mitzvah
*mitzvah* stops. The end is talking about there are two guys working
at it. Two guys working at it, you keep on working, I'm
going to take a five-minute break to say שמע Shema *shema* and
to דאווען *daven*. Now even that is interesting because that says in
the context of עוסק במצוה פטור מן המצוה *osek bemitzvah patur min
hamitzvah*, it's if the מצוה mitzvah *mitzvah* isn't going to be stopped,
then you do interrupt. And here it will be slowed down a
little, meaning the efficiency will slow down, you'll lose that person's work
for that time. So that's an interesting thing to think about עוסק
במצוה פטור מן המצוה *osek bemitzvah patur min hamitzvah*, as long as
the מצוה mitzvah. *mitzvah* is continuing even if you're stopping from doing
it, that
presumably that's not a problem. I'm just leaving it, we're not having
a full discussion of that right now. Anyway, back to our issue.
So that solves that problem. מכל מקום קשיא לרב micol makom kashya
l'Rav. *Mikol makom kashya lerav*, it's a problem to רב Rav *Rav*
because here it says you put on תפילין Tefillin. *tefillin* and then
you say קריאת שמע krias shema *krias shema*, and רב Rav *Rav*
did the opposite. So רב Rav כרבי יהושע בן קרחה סבירא ליה
*Rav kerabbi yehoshua ben korcha sevirah leih*. רב Rav *Rav* holds like
רבי Rebbi יהושע בן קרחה *Rabbi Yehoshua Ben Korcha*. What does this
have to do with רבי יהושע בן קרחה *Rabbi Yehoshua Ben Korcha*
of our משנה Mishnah. *mishna*? דאמר *De'amar*, because רבי יהושע בן קרחה
*Rabbi Yehoshua Ben Korcha* sets out a
sort of a priority order: עול מלכות שמים ol malchus shamayim, תחילה
*ol malchus shamayim techilah*, first there's the עול מלכות שמים ol malchus
shamayim, *ol malchus shamayim*, accepting the yoke of heaven, ואחר כך עול
מצוות *ve'acharkach ol mitzvos*, and then the מצוות *mitzvos*. So I said
you know that wasn't a chronological order, that was like a conceptual
order, but רב Rav *Rav* translated it into practice in what we
have to do first as we go about our day is first
we establish עול מלכות שמים ol malchus shamayim, *ol malchus shamayim* and
then we work on מצוות *mitzvos*. So I'm first going to say
שמע Shema *shema* which establishes עול מלכות שמים ol malchus shamayim *ol
malchus shamayim* and then I'm going to do the מצוה mitzvah *mitzvah*
of תפילין Tefillin *tefillin*. The doing of the מצוות *mitzvos* comes after
the establishing of עול מלכות שמים ol malchus shamayim *ol malchus shamayim*.
That's why he did the תפילין Tefillin *tefillin* later. So the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* says one minute, אימת דאמר רבי יהושע בן קרחה *eiman
de'amar rabbi yehoshua ben korcha*, when did רבי יהושע בן קרחה *Rabbi
Yehoshua Ben Korcha* say it? להקדים קריאה לקריאה *Lehakdim kriya lekriya*, that's
when you sort of if you have to say one or say
the other, right, you're going to say עול מלכות ol malchus, שמים
*ol malchus shamayim* before you say עול מצוות *ol mitzvos*. קריאה לעשייה
מי שמיע ליה *Kriya la'asiyah mi shamia leih*? He didn't say when
it actually came to doing מצוות *mitzvos* that that you first do
the saying and then you know before the doing. Now what's the
difference? So it could be two things. First of all it could
just be and this is a general question you know that the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* in קידושין *Kiddushin* has you know whether you know
which is greater, you know תלמוד או מעשה *talmud o ma'aseh*, learning
or doing? So maybe the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says you know if
we're talking theoretically, so if we're talking about the learning about it,
learning of A comes before the learning of B. But doing, doing
always takes priority. Meaning it could just be the question about doing
versus learning and doing always takes priority. It could be another point
also, it could be the point that I was telling you which
is a question about chronology, meaning in a sort of you know
in a somatic way or like in a you know sort of
in a theoretical way, first there's עול מלכות שמים malchus shamayim. *ol
malchus shamayim* and then there's עול מצוות *ol mitzvos*. If we're talking
about it, that's how we're going to lay out. Here's the foundation
of עול מלכות שמים malchus shamayim *ol malchus shamayim*, the foundation of
עול מצוות *ol mitzvos*. But that's not necessarily the order in which
you do things. Okay, there's something about how you talk about things
and how you sort of structure what the system is about and
then there's the order of which you do things which is not
necessarily the same. So that's what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says. That's,
I'm sorry, that does not explain why you would say שמע Shema
*shema* before putting on תפילין Tefillin. *tefillin*. ותו *Vetu*, and in addition,
מי סבר ליה כרבי יהושע בן קרחה *misavrah leih kerabbi yehoshua ben
korcha*?
What makes you think he holds like that? Meaning I'll give you
an evidence that he himself agrees that the order is תפילין Tefillin
*tefillin* and then שמע Shema *shema*. ואמר Va'amar, רב חייא בר אשי
Rav Chiya bar Ashi *Ve'amar rav chiya bar ashi*, did רב חייא
בר אשי Rav Chiya bar Ashi? *Rav Chiya Bar Ashi* say: זמנין
סגיאין הוי קאימנא קמיה דרב *zimnin sagi'in havei kamina kamei de'rav*, many
times I was standing in front of רב Rav *Rav*, presumably early
in the morning, ומקדים ומשא ידיה *umakdim umashi yadei*, he would get
up and wash his hands, ומברך *umivareich*, and he'd make a ברכה
bracha *bracha*, meaning ברכת התורה Birchat HaTorah. *birkas hatorah*, this is like
what we're talking about before that if you teach תורה *Torah* before
קריאת שמע Kriyat Shema *krias shema*, then you have to make ברכת
התורה Birchat HaTorah *birkas hatorah*. ומשני לן פרקין *Umashni lan pirkein*, he
would teach us our chapter of משנה Mishnah. *mishna*, ומניח תפילין Tefillin
*umaniah tefillin*, and then he'd put on תפילין Tefillin *tefillin*, והדר קורא
korei קריאת שמע Kriyat Shema *vehadar kore krias shema*, and then he'd
do שמע Shema *shema*. So you see he did תפילין Tefillin *tefillin*
before שמע Shema *shema*. So you really don't have to bring in
רבי יהושע בן קרחה *Rabbi Yehoshua Ben Korcha*, the two stories of
רב Rav *Rav* are contradicting themselves. One has him doing שמע Shema
*shema* and then תפילין Tefillin, *tefillin*, the other has him doing תפילין
Tefillin *tefillin* and then שמע Shema *shema*. Okay. רש״י *Rashi* by the
way says the problem is also that he was teaching תורה *Torah*
before שמע Shema *shema*, so he was also doing some מצוה mitzvah
*mitzvah* before doing עול מלכות שמים malchus shamayim? *ol malchus shamayim*, except
that's more interesting, his teaching תורה *Torah* focused as a מצוה mitzvah.
*mitzvah* as focused as you know as ללמוד או ללמד *lilmod o
leilameid*. Anyway, but the bigger question for bracketing רש"י Rashi is that
the order of תפילין Tefillin. and שמע Shema are reversed. Before we
said שמע Shema then תפילין, Tefillin. here we're saying תפילין Tefillin and
then שמע.
Shema, Oh, we do already set it that it doesn't follow like
רבי יהושע בן קרחה from
earlier, רב משרשיא. Rav Masharsheya.
I know. No, there we tried to say that it was based
on רבי יהושע בן קרחה. The reason he did שמע Shema. and
then תפילין Tefillin. is עול מלכות שמים malchus shamayim and then מצוות.
But here we're saying he did it in the normal way, he
did תפילין Tefillin. and then שמע. Shema So you could really take
out רבי יהושע בן קרחה. One story רב Rav did שמע Shema?
and תפילין Tefillin and in the second story he did תפילין Tefillin
and שמע. Shema Right? So how do we make sense of that?
Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says וכי תימא בדלא מטא זמן קריאת
שמע, V'chi teima badlo mata zman krias Shema, maybe, ah, here's the
reason. That the reason he did תפילין Tefillin and then שמע Shema,
is that really the first story is the fundamental, the real one.
He really does שמע Shema and תפילין. Tefillin This one time, you
know, he was doing or there were times he would wake up
early and it was too early to say שמע. Shema And presumably
it's interesting, it suggests that there could be a time where it's
appropriate to put on תפילין Tefillin. and not yet appropriate for שמע.
Shema And תפילין Tefillin is normally משיכיר. mi-she-yakir. So משיכיר mi-she-yakir we
normally assume is the right time to say שמע, Shema although there
are opinions that maybe the time of שמע Shema isn't until נץ.
Netz. But it's very funny, those are more marginal opinions. But the
גמרא Gemara is saying here's maybe the explanation. Normally he would do
שמע Shema and תפילין. Tefillin? The times that he would do תפילין
Tefillin. and שמע Shema was when it wasn't yet the time for
שמע Shema. and he had to wait and do שמע Shema, later.
אי הכי, Ei hachi, the גמרא Gemara, says if that's true, מה
אסידותיה דרב חייא בר אשי? mai asidusei d'Rav Chiya bar Ashi? Why
does רב Rav חייא בר אשי bother telling us this story? Then
it's not, you know, we can't really learn something from it because
the order of שמע Shema. and תפילין tefillin, is not significant because
it had to do with the fact that the time wasn't there
yet. So the גמרא Gemara says no, he would tell us the
story not because of the שמע Shema תפילין tefillin, order, he told
us the story for another point.
לאפוקי ממאן דאמר למשנה אין צריך לברך קמשמע לן דאף למשנה נמי
צריך לברך. L'apukei mi-man d'amar l'mishnah ain tzarich l'varch, kamashmalan d'af l'mishnah
nami tzarich l'varch. The reason he told the story, the שמע shema
and the תפילין tefillin. were completely incidental. Maybe the reason he told
the story was to tell us that when he got up to
teach, he would make ברכת התורה. Birchat HaTorah Because he was teaching
before שמע. shema? Why is that a חידוש? chiddush? Because we learned
earlier that some people say you don't make a ברכת התורה when
you're teaching משנה, Mishnah only when you're teaching פסוקים. psukim. And it
says here מתני לן פרקין, masni lan pirkin, he taught us our
משנה. mishna. So maybe the point of this had nothing to do
with שמע shema, and תפילין, tefillin, the point of this was just
to tell you you make ברכת התורה on משנה. Mishnah Okay, so
now we somehow neutralize that story. But the גמרא Gemara is not
done. The גמרא Gemara says like this,
מכל מקום קשיא לרב. The גמרא Gemara says okay fine, but we're
still bothered. Why are we still bothered? It doesn't really explain it.
Maybe because at the end of the day they don't buy that
answer. In one version we have רב Rav doing תפילין tefillin and
then שמע, shema, the other שמע shema and then תפילין. tefillin. Or
maybe what the גמרא Gemara said before, the גמרא Gemara just takes
it for granted that you
don't do the מצוה of שמע shema before you're going to do
the מצוה of תפילין. tefillin Either for the reason either that I
said that like practice precedes the talking about it, or we're going
to see a minute later which probably is interesting the גמרא Gemara
hasn't brought in yet, but the idea that you don't talk about
the מצוה of תפילין tefillin if you're not wearing the תפילין. tefillin
So the גמרא, Gemara although the גמרא Gemara could have reconciled this,
the גמרא Gemara is still bothered. It doesn't like the idea that
רב Rav? is saying שמע shema, before תפילין. tefillin So how does
it reconcile? Let me just read the answer. So how does the
גמרא Gemara. reconcile? So the גמרא Gemara says שלוחא הוא דעוות. shlucha
hu d'avis. Fine, the messenger made a mistake. What does that mean?
The messenger what? So רש"י Rashi says it means the guy who
was supposed to bring רב's Rebbi, תפילין tefillin, was late. So basically
you're right, רב Rebbi did like everybody else does. רב Rebbi did
like the משנה said about when you're, you know, about when you're
digging the thing for the מת mase and so on, and רב
Rebbi. did like this, רב Rebbi put on תפילין tefillin, and then
wait a minute, רב put on תפילין tefillin and then he did
the שמע shema like all the other, like everybody does and like
all the evidence. The one story that רב did the שמע shema,
and then the תפילין tefillin was when his assistant was late bringing
him his תפילין. tefillin So what was he going to do? And
that gets into תוספות's Tosafot discussion, what happens if you get your
pair of תפילין tefillin. late and you're between שמע shema. and שמונה
עשרה, Shmoneh Esreh, what do you do?
Two questions. First of all, it doesn't say חדא זימנא chada zimna
רב משרשיא. Rav Masharsheya. רב משרשיא Rav Masharsheya sounds like it happened
usually. Secondly, you could have glossed over this but you mentioned that
you know it was according to רש"י Rashi it was a problem
that he was learning before, I mean the גמרא gemara. says, so
does that mean that you know any of us shouldn't be going
to the second מנין minyan and learning דף יומי? Daf Yomi? Right.
So
that's way רש"י Rashi read it anyway, and let's bracket that question
for now. Okay, so
the גמרא gemara says like this, אמר עולא amar Ulla what?
How could רב משרשיא Rav Masharsheya have been learning with רב? Is
this רב חייא בר אשי? Is that משרשיא? Masharsheya? Yeah. And his
son, there's so many generations.
Yeah,
I'm not, I'm not great on that. Does שטיינזלץ Steinsaltz help in
giving you the date? Sometimes he gives you the dates. Alright, I'll
have to check on the dates. Okay, so anyway, but Michael in
a way is right because it is a larger question that you
can't do anything before שמע shema? even like learn? I mean we've
talked about not doing personal things before דאווענען, davening, but is it
anything? Or is there a particular issue here about תפילין? tefillin, On
one hand the גמרא gemara seems to make it a global issue,
but now we're going to hone in on the particular nature of
wearing, of not wearing, of if you're saying שמע shema. you should
be wearing תפילין. tefillin, So let's take a look. Well, we're not
going to raise that as a question, but we're going to reframe
the issue. Okay, so אמר עולא, amar Ulla, so says עולא, Ulla,
כל הקורא קריאת שמע... kol hakore krias Shema... תפילין, tefillin anybody who
says שמע shema without תפילין, tefillin. now here it's not again this
larger issue of ללמוד, עול מלכות, או מצוות, o mitzvos, מצוות, just
שמע shema, and תפילין. tefillin If you say שמע Shema. without תפילין,
tefillin כאילו מעיד עד שקר בעצמו, k'ilu me'id ed sheker b'atzmo, it's
like you're testifying falsely against yourself. You're saying that there's a מצוה
to wear תפילין tefillin and you're not wearing תפילין. tefillin Now רש"י
Rashi says לעצמו l'atzmo is a euphemism. It's like you're giving false
testimony about God. You're saying, you know,
God has told us to wear תפילין tefillin? and sometimes you're making
it false because you're not doing it. I don't exactly get why
רש"י Rashi has to say it's a euphemism. The one who's doing
the wrong thing here is you, not God. So it's like you're
saying we are commanded to wear תפילין tefillin and then you're falsely
testifying as if you're doing it, as if, you know, you're that's
what you do, and here you're showing that you're not doing it.
So I don't get why רש"י Rashi makes it said it's as
if you're saying something false about God. Wait until later? No, so
this is, oh, so the גמרא gemara, doesn't, interestingly the גמרא gemara
doesn't say that and I should mention that the reason the גמרא
gemara doesn't say that about טלית tallis is because by טלית tallis
there's no מצוה to always wear טלית, tallis, there's a מצוה if
you're wearing a four-cornered garment to have ציצית on it.
So this idea of כאילו מעיד עד שקר k'ilu me'id ed sheker
is very particular about תפילין tefillin. and therefore right, it's very much
about תפילין for שמע, Shema not about טלית tallis before you get
to פרשת ציצית, that is not a concern of the גמרא. gemara.
Okay, so גמרא gemara says like this: אמר רבי חייא בר אבא
אמר רבי יוחנן, amar Rabbi Chiya bar Abba amar Rabbi Yochanan, כאילו
הקריב עולה בלא מנחה וזבח בלא נסכים, k'ilu hikriv olah b'lo mincha
v'zevach b'lo nesachim, quoting the language of the פסוק, pasuk, עולה מנחה
זבח ונסכים. olah mincha zevach v'nesachim. Like you brought an עולה olah
without a מנחה, mincha, without its accompanying מנחה, mincha, and you brought
the זבח, zevach, the sacrifice without its accompanying נסכים, nesachim, which is
actually a little lighter. It's not like, you know, you're making a
mockery of the whole thing. It's just saying, you know, you didn't
do the thing in the fullest way. You spoke about it but
you didn't accompany it, you didn't translate it into action. Meaning maybe
we're willing to take a little bit more of a generous approach.
We understand that eventually you're going to wear תפילין, it's not like
you're declaring a falsehood and you're making a mockery, but still to
be declaring it and talking about it without actually embodying it and
doing it, that is a lack of a full fulfillment of what
it means to be saying the שמע. Shema So that is important
then because it also is an interesting question and this is actually
debated in the פוסקים, poskim, when you say שמע Shema, without תפילין,
right, does it mean, you know, is it like a worse, is
it an independent problem, כאילו מעיד עד שקר, k'ilu me'id ed sheker,
or to some degree is it also saying that it's a lesser
קיום kiyum of the שמע? Shema, The same way you said that
שמע Shema? without the ברכות brachos is a lesser fulfillment of the
שמע, Shema is the שמע Shema without the
תפילין an independent problem, it's a bad thing to do, or is
it like the last statement, it's not as much of a better
fulfillment of the שמע Shema is to say the שמע Shema in
an embodied way and not just to say it without its translating
into action? So that is an interesting question and it comes up
as I said when you wake up very late and it's almost
סוף זמן קריאת שמע sof zman krias shema and you try to
like rush to say שמע Shema with תפילין and with ברכות קריאת
שמע birchos krias shema and you might miss סוף זמן קריאת שמע.
sof zman krias shema. So it's actually a question, if you have
to choose, which do you choose? Do you say if you could
put on תפילין and say שמע Shema, or you could say ברכות
קריאת שמע birchos krias shema and say שמע Shema but you can't
do both because of the time, which one do you do? And
actually the פסק psak is that you do ברכות קריאת שמע, birchos
krias shema, not the תפילין. So that at the end of the
day it's clear that the ברכות קריאת שמע birchos krias shema are
more central to the fulfillment, the rabbinic idea of the fulfillment of
שמע Shema than the wearing of the תפילין, but this last point
does say also that that's an aspect of the fullest קיום kiyum
of the שמע. Shema Dov, you wanted to say something?
I think that we only say this in this context but I
don't think they ever say that you shouldn't teach the פרשה of
תפילין, you know, if you're a teacher and you're not wearing תפילין
or any other מצוה.
Right, right,
that's a good point.
Yeah, I mean, again, I guess,
I mean, I'm trying to think if whether the difference is that
when you're teaching it you're talking more theoretical and when you're saying
it like this you're talking more like not like you're sort of
declaring our obligation so it's a little bit more, you know, it's
less theoretical and more sort of imminent, or is the difference that
just this has been ritualized and as a ritual and part of
the תפילה tefillah we want to sort of fully embody it at
that moment is probably more of the answer.
Yes, but the עולה and the מנחה, mincha, because you know we
learned that some things can be done later even after עשרה ימים,
asara yomim, right, so
you know so that's exactly I think his point, which is exactly
it, is that okay, I'm not saying what you did was like
a total, you know,
right, or like a total affront, but it's not the ideal way
which meant bringing it all together. Okay, yes.
So if he's late in the morning, yes, you want to say
the שמע, Shema you say the two ברכות brachos first?
If you if you have the time, yeah and but you only
have a very limited amount of time, right, then you know just
right go straight to the ברכות brachos of קריאת שמע kriyat shema,
and then say the שמע. Shema What, I skip פסוקי דזמרה, pesukei
d'zimra, start with the ברכות brachos of קריאת שמע Kriat Shema then
go through שמונה עשרה Shmoneh Esreh because then you can't say the
שמע Shema, without saying the end ברכות brachos and then you have
to be סומך גאולה לתפילה. somech geulah l'tfila.
I mean, say you're really late and you want to do your
whole דאוונען davening but you just want to say שמע Shema, first
because you want to get that in. Do you have to say
the ברכות berachos before and after, or can you just say שמע?
Shema, So then you're ask- so what you're asking is another question,
which is the personal experience of תפילה tefillah and כוונה kavanah versus
the sort of the more formal aspects of it. Because what I
would tell you is from a perspective of what's the- formally, what's
the full fulfillment is to say שמע, Shema ברכות, berachos, שמע, Shema,
but then you have to end with the end ברכות berachos and
then do שמונה עשרה. shemoneh esrei. But then your response is, yeah,
but then I'm not being able to really put- get my כוונה
kavanah of דאוונען. davening. So then it becomes a question, what's the
tradeoff? Better you should do these formal things and have- and not
have כוונה kavanah or better you should have more כוונה kavanah and
just do שמע Shema without the ברכות? berachos? But you would not
do ברכות berachos and שמע Shema, and without the rest. Either you're
going to do the ברכות, berachos, שמע, Shema? end ברכות, berachos, שמונה
עשרה, shemoneh esrei, and then- or you're going to do just the
שמע and then do everything in order. Okay? But then that becomes,
as I said, that's a bigger, interesting discussion about your personal כוונה
kavanah versus some of these more formal aspects. Okay, let's go back
to the
גמרא. gemara אמר רב יוחנן, amar rav yochanan, הרוצה שיקבל עליו עול
מלכות שמים שלמה, harotzeh sheyekabel alav ol malchus shamayim sheleimah, somebody who
wants to have the full acceptance of the עול מלכות שמים, malchus
shamayim? so we're getting to again the theme of שמע, but now
let's take a look. Now we're going to tie it into things
we spoke about before.
So, יפנה ויטול, yifneh viyitol, first of all go to the bathroom
before you
דאוונען, daven, ויטול ידיו, viyitol yadav, wash your hands, ויניח תפילין, veyanich
tefillin, put on תפילין. Interestingly- no mention of טלית, tallis, because that's
more, you know, optional as it were, and
the גמרא gemara later will discuss טלית tallis as part of שמונה
עשרה. shemoneh esrei. ויקרא קריאת שמע ויתפלל, veyikra krias shema veyitpallel, and
say קריאת שמע and דאוונען, daven, וזו היא מלכות שמים שלמה, vezo
hi malchus shamayim sheleimah, this is a full מלכות שמים. malchus shamayim,
So first of all, right, it's not like exactly, which is interesting,
because- that's a good point, right, so it's like what are those
things doing? Those optional. But anyway, but the- but the point about
framing it as מלכות שמים malchus shamayim. is also interesting. Why is
תפילה tefillah מלכות שמים? malchus shamayim? I thought מלכות שמים malchus shamayim.
was focused on שמע. But part of what this is doing is,
you know, the question before the גמרא Gemara is shouldn't we start
with מלכות שמים? malchut shamayim Shouldn't we start with שמע? So here
the answer is no, no, no, to get the experience of מלכות
שמים, malchut shamayim you have to do some things leading up to
שמע. So you prepare yourself, you go to the bathroom so you're
not, you know, sort of obviously distracted or whatever, that would be
inappropriate anyway. You wash your hands, that's preparing yourself, you know, conceptually,
physically, cleansing yourself. Putting on תפילין is getting you in a particular
mindset, and then that sets up the stage for the מלכות שמים.
malchut shamayim, So it's in a way it's an answer to the
גמרא, Gemara shouldn't you start with מלכות שמים? malchut shamayim No, no,
this allows you to get to a full מלכות שמים. malchut shamayim
But even there the question is what's the idea about דאוונען, davening,
where does that fit in? And that's- תפילה tefillah?
is the climax.
Well right, that's- but again it's- it's not the קבלת עול מלכות
שמים, malchut shamayim, it's the translation of the עול מלכות שמים, malchut
shamayim which is the idea of סמיכת גאולה לתפילה, semichas geulah litefillah,
you know. The שמע is our accepting and acknowledging of like God
is our God and our obligations and what God has done for
us, and then once we're sort of in that relationship and we've
acknowledged it, it translates into allowing us to then turn to God
and pray to God. So in a way it right, it's the
translation of the עול מלכות שמים, malchut shamayim. but the- but- and
I think that's the point, that this all works together as a
package. Yes.
Qualified for women as well?
So yeah, that was implicitly Charlie's issue as well and I've sort
of been, you know, sort of like glossing over that. Obviously the
גמרא Gemara here is talking to men and assuming, you know, men
wearing תפילין and that whole thing, and it's not addressing the issue
about what does this say to women who aren't wearing תפילין and
you know, and they're not- you know, and they're not having that
experience. Are you saying that's not עול מלכות שמים malchut shamayim. תפילה?
tefillah. Is what Charlie asked. Are you saying that no, it's for
men who have the obligation this is a necessary part of it
but for women it's not? You know, so the גמרא Gemara obviously
is just completely- the women issue is invisible in this גמרא.
Gemara In modern versions today, would women follow the same track basically?
Minus the תפילין or with the תפילין? Right. Yeah, I mean the-
other than the תפילין I don't think the גמרא Gemara is otherwise
sort of sees this as gender-related, but it's just ignoring the question
of women and assuming we're talking to men and that they're wearing
תפילין. Yeah.
Just a question. I mean as far as I know, like you
know, the going to the bathroom is pretty much a הלכה halakha
that you know, it's better to like miss a couple of things-
Well
that has to do also with דאוונען. davening. There's a separate issue,
I don't want to get into it now. There's a separate issue
about having to go to the bathroom when you דאוונען, daven, that
that's a real פסול pasul and that's- you know, the גמרא Gemara
actually says your דאוונען davening is פסול pasul if you did it
or whatever. That's another discussion. This is talking fundamentally about the experience
of the שמע, where there the idea of having to go to
the bathroom is not so much of a פסול pasul but it's
part of this issue of preparing yourself and עול מלכות שמים malchut
shamayim תפילה. tefillah Although in the end you wind up דאוונען davening
as well. So let's keep on reading. אמר רבי חייא, amar rabbi
chiya, אמר רבי חייא בר אבא אמר יוחנן, amar rabbi chiya bar
abba amar yochanan, כל הנפנה, kol hanifneh, again, anybody who first goes
to the bathroom,
ונוטל ידיו ומניח תפילין וקורא קריאת שמע ומתפלל, vinoteil yadav umeinich tefillin
vekorei krias shema umitpallel, you do all these things like in maybe
in this order without interrupting anything else, and this sort of is
a very package here, so מעלה עליו הכתוב כאילו בנה מזבח והקריב
עליו קרבן. maaleh alav hakatuv k'ilu banah mizbeiach ve'hikriv alav korban. So
before we had your קרבן korban without the נסכים, nesachim, now we
have it's like you בנה מזבח banah mizbeiach and you put the
קרבן korban on. So it's not so much the accoutrement, but the
בנה מזבח, banah mizbeiach, right? The גמרא Gemara. is very clear with
its metaphors before. It was, you have the whole package, you have
the thing with everything that comes with it, the fullest fulfillment of
a קרבן. korban. Here the idea is you went to the effort
to prepare the altar, you built the altar and then you put
on the קרבן. korban. So normally we just come and we show
up with our קרבן, korban, but here no, you're really preparing the
basis for then bringing the קרבן. korban. Okay, so דכתיב dechtiv as
the פסוק pasuk says, ארחץ בנקיון כפי ואסובבה את מזבחך ה'. Erchatz
benikayon kapai va'asovevah et mizbechachah Hashem. I will wash with cleanliness my
hands and then I will go around your altar, God. So first
you prepare yourself, so that's the washing of the hands, but the
כמאן דאמר k'man d'amar it's the whole package of preparing yourself and
then you bring the קרבן. korban. אמר ליה רבא, Amar lei Rava,
לא סבר ליה מר כאילו טבל? lo savar lei mar ke'ilu taval?
You should have also said it's like you went to the מקוה
mikvah just by washing your hands. Why? דכתיב ארחץ בנקיון, Dechtiv erchatz
benikayon, I will wash in cleanliness, ולא כתיב ארחץ בכפי, velo chtiv
erchatz bekapai, I will wash my hands. I mean it says first
ארחץ בנקיון כפי. erchatz benikayon kapai. So Rava's reading it just by
washing your hands it's like you cleansed your entire self. Okay, so
the גמרא Gemara doesn't have an answer. Anyway, that seems to be
a little off-point. We're not talking about the value of washing your
hands per se; we're talking about how it all leads up to
the saying of שמע. Anyway.
Yes, just for one second, on this word שלמה. shleimah. Yes. You
seem to be describing it almost as an end result, talking about
the קבלה. kabbalah. Okay.
That you prepared yourself and
everything else. Right. You see where you're going. Go ahead.
Just the possibility that really what it is is that it's your
understanding of what מלכות שמים is and that it's not just the
prime mover, it now is the God that is in your daily
experience.
What he's saying is that the מלכות שמים is a fuller מלכות
שמים, meaning not your experience was fuller, but that your מלכות שמים
is not just theoretical. What מלכות שמים means is it means it
translates into how do you prepare to encounter God. It means that
if you have the מלכות שמים, then it translates into being able
into a prayer relationship with God. So the מלכות שמים is a
full מלכות שמים.
Right. In the second reading where it says שלמה shleimah is a
funny מלכות שמים.
No, that's a very I like I appreciate that. That's a very
beautiful idea. The גמרא Gemara afterwards of כאילו בנה מזבח ke'ilu banah
mizbe'ach talks about sort of your effort and your preparation. But what
you're saying is no, the מלכות שמים is שלמה. shleimah. How does
that translate into what how you act in your life? That's a
beautiful idea. Thank you. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara, says like
this.
Okay, אמר ליה רבינא לרבא. Amar lei Ravina le-Rava. So Ravina said
to Rava, חזי מר האי צורבא מרבנן דאתא ממערבא? Chazi mar hai
tzurba merabbanan de'ata mima'arava? Did you see that student of the rabbis
that came from the west, Israel? ואמר, and he said, מי שאין
לו מים לרחוץ ידיו, Mi she'ein lo mayim lirchotz yadav, if you
don't have water to wash your hands, מקנח ידיו בעפר ובצרור ובקסמית.
mekane'ach yadav be'afar uvetzror uvekasmit. You can clean your hands with like
dirt and pebbles and like what's קסמית? kasmit? Wood chips. Thank you.
I never got cleaning your hands with dirt unless the point is
it's not that they're, it says more that they have gunk on
them and the dirt, the friction is getting the gunk off. It's
not that they're dirty. Okay. Anyway, so it says so where did
so did you see this? Where's this from? אמר ליה, Amar lei,
שפיר קאמר. shapir ka'amar. Actually that's good. He says good. מי כתיב
ארחץ במים? Mi chtiv erchatz bemayim? It doesn't say I'll wash my
hands with water. בנקיון כתיב. Benikayon ktiv. I'll wash them with cleanliness.
כל מידי דמנקי. Kol midei demanki. Anything that cleans as long as
it gets the dirt off, doesn't have to be water.
What's cleaner than dirt? Right. So okay, exactly. דהא רב חסדא לייט
אמאן דמהדר אמיא בעידן צלותא. De-ha Rav Chisda layit aman demahader amaya
be'idan tzluta. Rav Chisda would curse somebody that would be looking after
water when it's time for davening. If you've got to get to
davening, don't postpone your davening because of water. Just cleanse your hands
with anything. So the גמרא Gemara says והני מילי לקריאת שמע. vahani
milei le-Kri'at Shema. That's when it comes to שמע that we can
do sort of dirt other than water. אבל לתפילה, Aval litfillah, when
it comes to שמונה עשרה, Shemoneh Esrei, מהדר. mahader. You should try
to get specifically water. ועד כמה? Ve'ad kamma? How much? עד פרסה.
Ad parsa. Even if you have to travel a פרסה, parsa, like
2000 מיל, mil, which is three-fifths of a mile or something like
that. והני מילי לקמיה. Vahani milei lekameih. That's if you're traveling in
that direction, then you have to wait until you get to the
water. אבל לאחוריה, Aval le'achoreih, if you're going if it's behind you,
you have to retrace your steps assuming you're on a journey. אפילו
מיל אינו חוזר. Afilu mil eino chozer. Then we don't ask you
to retrace your steps even a מיל, mil, which is like a
you know how
what's a מיל? mil? It's basically how long it takes to walk.
What? Yes, 2000 אמות. amos. Right. So it's whatever. It's like
three-fifths of a mile. That מיל mil is three-fifths of a mile.
Right. A פרסה parsa is a פרסה parsa is how many מיל?
mil?
I can't
believe I forgot this שיעור. shiur. Is it four מיל?
mil? A מיל mil is about three-fifths of a mile. Yeah. No,
so a פרסה parsa is ten מיל? mil?
I'm trying to remember. I can't believe I forgot. Anyway, so the
גמרא Gemara says מיל הוא דאינו חוזר. mil hu de'eino chozer. Oh,
four מיל. mil. Thank you. Okay, fine. Four מיל. mil. Sorry. Okay,
thank you. Thank you. Okay, I got confused. All right, right. A
פרסה parsa is four מיל. mil. So it says going forward... You
don't have to go forward for a פרסה, parsa, you know, even
a פרסה parsa which is four מיל, mil, which is about, whatever
it is, about three miles, but backwards you don't even have to
go backwards a מיל, mil, which is three-fifths of a mile. So
the גמרא Gemara says מיהו דאינו חוזר mihu deino chozer so
fine, so a מיל mil you don't have to go back. הפחות
ממיל, hapachos mi'mil, anything less than that חוזר chozer you would have
to go back. Now, that maybe is the הלכה halacha except here's
the issue. First of all, תוספות Tosafot doesn't have this whole גרסא.
girsa. The גמרא Gemara sort of contradicts itself. It says you shouldn't
postpone your דאווענען, davenen, תפילה tefillah, for water, you use this, and
then it says, oh, I'm only talking about שמע not תפילה, tefillah
תפילה you actually do postpone. But you just said you don't postpone
your דאווענען, davenen, specifically it said דאווענען. davenen. Okay, so there's a
little bit of a problem there.
So תוספות Tosafot basically doesn't have the whole גרסא girsa and he
says this whole discussion about how much you have to wait for
water going forward or going back, if you're on a trip or
whatever, is all about washing your hands for bread. It's not about
דאווענען. davenen. And תוספות Tosafot takes out this whole rest of this
גמרא. Gemara So the issue is really we're not going to resolve
it right now, but just to raise the point that the need
for water for דאווענען davenen and for שמע, and surely for שמע,
maybe even for דאווענען, davenen, you know, it's really more about cleanliness
than about a ritual washing with water. Whereas for bread it clearly
is much more about a ritual washing with water. That's where we
actually have a ברכה bracha. for washing your hands, although true, first
thing in the morning you do have a ברכה. bracha Anyway, but,
and there, there's more demands about how much long you have to
wait and journey out of your way etc. in order to get
water for washing. Charlie.
So we can safely use these water-free hand sanitizers for שמע?
Well, again, it's still לכתחילה l'chatchilah of water, but the question is
are you postponing, right, if water's not available, right. But I'm bracketing,
I'm not talking הלכה למעשה halacha l'maaseh now about this point about
how much it's a demand for שמונה עשרה, Shemoneh Esrei, is that
in the שמע category or is that in the bread category?
So here's what I'm not understanding, I mean, קריאת שמע is a
חיוב דאורייתא. chiyuv d'oraita. Right. But washing your hands for bread is
a rabbinic enactment, right? So why are we more מחמיר machmir for?
Because the washing your hands for קריאת שמע is not a חיוב
דאורייתא. chiyuv d'oraita. But washing your hands when we'll get to washing,
we'll talk about it. Washing your hands like, you know, there's whole
stories about people in prison and wouldn't eat because of all that
type of thing. It has to do with the world of טומאה
וטהרה tumah v'taharah and the bread is like the תרומה terumah for
the כהנים kohanim and so on. And as we know from having
just learned קדשים, Kodashim, there was a lot of stringencies on נטילה
netilah associated to issues around the טומאה וטהרה tumah v'taharah which is
not the same issue here which is more about cleanliness but not
about טומאה וטהרה. tumah v'taharah. Okay, so we'll talk about that more
when we get to the issue of bread.
Even though you're like being טהור tahor for like things?
It's not the same thing. There it's about eating bread which was
like touching food and touching תרומה terumah and was directly tapping into
the world of טומאה וטהרה. tumah v'taharah. Here it's more about הכון
לקראת אלוקיך ישראל, hachon likrat elokecha yisrael, you know, it's more about
the cleanliness aspect. But we'll talk about that more. Let's take a
look, let's get a little bit further. Next משנה. הקורא את שמע
ולא השמיע לאזנו יצא. hakorei et shema v'lo hishmia l'ozno yatza. If
you say the שמע and you did not hear what you were
saying, you fulfilled your obligation. דברי רבי יהודה. divrei rabbi yehuda. That's
what רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says. רבי יוסי אומר, rabbi yosi omer,
רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi says, that's an insert if you look at
the side, רבי יוסי אומר rabbi yosi omer says לא יצא, lo
yatza, you didn't fulfill your obligation, you have to hear what you're
saying. קרא ולא דקדק באותיותיו. kara v'lo dikdek b'otiotav. Let's say you
read it but you were not, you were sloppy in your articulation.
רבי יוסי אומר יצא, rabbi yosi omer yatza, you still fulfilled your
obligation. רבי יהודה אומר לא יצא, rabbi yehuda omer lo yatza, you
did not. Now I must tell you that it doesn't line up
as much as I would like it to because I would expect
that the same person that says that you have to be able
to hear would say you have to articulate well, that both of
those are more demands about the ritual of saying, and the one
that says you don't have to hear would also say you don't
have to articulate so well, but the גמרא Gemara actually splits the
vote. Okay, or whatever, crosses the vote. We'll see how we פסק'ן.
pasken. הקורא למפרע לא יצא, hakorei l'mafrea lo yatza, if you read
out of order you're not יוצא. yotzei. קרא וטעה, kara v'ta'ah, let's
say you
read and you made a mistake.
What? Yeah, the פסוקים psukim out of order. קרא וטעה, kara v'ta'ah,
let's say you read and you made a mistake and then you
know you read the whole thing and then you realized that you
skipped over one פסוק pasuk or you said one פסוק pasuk so
incorrectly that it didn't count. יחזור למקום שטעה, yachzor l'makom sheta'ah, you
can't just make up the פסוק. pasuk. You have to go back
to where you made the mistake and continue forward because otherwise you
would be saying it out of order.
Yeah. Most people haven't written? No, they didn't. And yet it keeps
saying קורא korei. is read as though it's written. Right.
And it's קריאת שמע,
right, and it's a written text, right. You go back, in your
mind you don't go back so much, right? And it uses the
word קורא.
Right and then it just implies and it uses these types of
things by המגילה hamegillah as well. קורא את המגילה korei et hamegillah
out of order, going back למקום l'makom etc. No, I understand, that's
an interesting question. That's an interesting question. It's true that you know
the whole function of the שליח ציבור shliach tzibur was that so
many people, you know, a, who didn't know it, a, weren't literate
and didn't know it בעל פה. ba'al peh. The question is how
many people, you know, how much was שמע actually a written text
that people were reading from? That is a really interesting question. What?
Because of the word it's מקרא, mikra, it's פסוקים, psukim, right, right,
right. Yeah, so right, that's the alternative, that you're just using that
verb because you're talking
about
reading
פסוקים, psukim, it's about reciting פסוקים. psukim. Right. Right. It's a good
point. It's a good point. I don't know if anybody's looked into
that. Okay, let's see what the גמרא Gemara, says. מאי טעמא דרבי
יוסי? Mai taama d'Rabbi Yose? What's the reason of רבי יוסי Rabbi
Yose that he says that you have to hear?
דכתיב שמע השמע לאזנך מה שאתה מוציא מפיך. Dechtiv Shema, hashmea l'oznecha
mah she-atah motzi mipicha. Let your ears hear what is coming out
of your lips. Right. And ורבנן סברי Ve-Rabbanan savri the תנא קמא
Tanna Kamma who we find out is רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda holds
שמע בכל לשון שאתה שומע. Shema be-chol lashon she-atah sho'mea. No, שמע
just means it could be in other languages, but it doesn't mean
that you have to hear it. דרבי יוסי תרתי שמע מינה. D'Rabbi
Yose tarti shema mina. And before the גמרא, Gemara if you remember,
said it was one or the other. Here the גמרא Gemara is
willing to say, yeah, you can learn, you can have both positions.
שמע could mean, it could mean languages, and it could also other
languages, and it could also mean, though, you have to actually hear.
Now the question is: does it mean it has to be audible,
or does it mean you have to hear? Okay, and the גמרא
Gemara is going to turn to that right now. Let's take a
look. תנן התם. Tnan hatam. We taught over there in תרומות. Trumos.
חרש המדבר ואינו שומע. Cheresh hamedaber ve-eino shomea. If somebody is mute
and he I excuse me, is deaf, but he can speak but
he can't hear, לא יתרום. lo yitrom. He cannot take תרומה. Truma.
Why? Because not that he's not considered a full בר דעת, bar
da'at, a person of, you know, full legal standing, but because you
make a ברכה bracha before תרומה Truma and he won't be able
to hear the ברכה bracha he's making. So here we see it's
very because he's deaf, so here we see it's very clearly about
not just being audible but about the person himself hearing it. And
you should you're supposed to make a ברכה bracha, before taking תרומה.
Truma. ואם תרם, Ve-im taram, but if you did it, תרומתו תרומה,
trumato Truma, then it still counts because, okay, you didn't make a
ברכה, bracha, but you still took תרומה. Truma. So it's בדיעבד be-di'avad
it works. So the גמרא Gemara says like this. So first of
all, the first thing we see that the גמרא Gemara is going
to bring this in the conversation is it's very much about you
hearing yourself, not about it just being audible. And that's interesting because
audible, I could have understood. I could have said it's not speech
unless it's audible, unless it has the ability to be heard. It
doesn't count as saying it. But here to say that you have
to hear it, that if somebody else hears it and you don't,
you're not יוצא yotzei according to רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose is very
strange. But to some degree, not so strange when it comes to
the issue of שמע, because the שמע is like a declaration to
yourself, right? It's not a prayer. תפילה שמונה עשרה. Tfilah Shmoneh Esrei.
שמע is not prayer, שמע is declaring. שמע ישראל השם אלוקינו השם
אחד. Shema Yisrael Hashem Elokeinu Hashem Echad. Who are you declaring it
to? In a way, you're declaring it first and foremost to yourself.
So if you're not hearing what you yourself are saying, to some
degree, it's not the same type of a declaration because it's not
having that impact on you. So דוקא שמונה עשרה, davka Shmoneh Esrei,
you know, might be a very different story. Might be you're not
supposed to hear. That's fundamentally to God and it could be, you
know, בלחש be-lachash and so on. But שמע has this idea, it's
not just audible, at least according to רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yose, but
you being able to hear it.
It's it's interesting. This, this, this, this, this, this places a big
burden on anyone who's deaf.
They can never fulfill the מצוה of שמע and never take תרומה.
Truma. Yeah, so it's a good thing we're not going to פסקן
pasken like רבי יוסי. Rabbi Yose. Okay, fine. So let's see how
the גמרא Gemara continues. It says like this. So the גמרא Gemara
says like this: מאן תנא חרש המדבר ואינו שומע? Man tanna cheresh
hamedaber ve-eino shomea? Who's the one that says that somebody who's who
can speak but can't hear, בדיעבד אין לכתחילה לא, be-di'avad in lechatchila
lo, can only be יוצא yotzei the מצוה of שמע, can do
the מצוות, can be do תרומה Truma בדיעבד be-di'avad but not
לכתחילה? lechatchila? אמר רב חסדא רבי יוסי, Amar Rav Chisda Rabbi Yose,
it's רבי יוסי. Rabbi Yose. דתנן הקורא שמע ולא השמיע לאזנו יצא
דברי רבי יהודה. Detnan hakorei Shema velo hishmia l'ozno yatza divrei Rabbi
Yehuda. Here it has it's רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda holds רבי יוסי
אומר לא יצא. Rabbi Yose omer lo yatza. So רבי יוסי Rabbi
Yose says normally if you can't hear, it's no good. So that
fits into the תרומה Truma case. עד כאן לא קאמר רבי יוסי
לא יצא אלא לגבי קריאת שמע דאורייתא. Ad kan lo ka'amar Rabbi
Yose lo yatza ela legabi Kriat Shema d'Oraita. When did he say
you're not יוצא? yotzei? That's by קריאת שמע which is biblical. אבל
תרומה משום ברכה הוא. Aval Truma mishum bracha hu. By תרומה, Truma,
the whole problem was the ברכה, bracha. right? And therefore ברכה דרבנן
ולא בברכה תליא מילתא. bracha d'Rabbanan velo b'vracha talya milta. That's only
Rabbinic and it's not hinging on the ברכה. bracha Now what does
that mean? רש"י Rashi interprets it's sort of two issues here. One
is the ברכה bracha and one is the דרבנן. d'Rabbanan. רש"י Rashi
says what it means is רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose would say for
Rabbinic מצוות you are יוצא yotzei even if you can't hear. Okay,
and the ברכה bracha, is only a Rabbinic מצוה. But there's an
easier way to read the גמרא, Gemara that תוספות Tosafot says, "Okay,
you didn't fulfill the ברכה, bracha who cares? You still it was
still good תרומה." Truma. Okay, but anyway, either way, the גמרא Gemara
understands that this is the position of רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yose, that
the problem is that you can't hear and that's only a רבי
יוסי Rabbi Yose problem.
So then the גמרא Gemara is going to say the following. The
גמרא Gemara says like this: וממאי דרבי יוסי היא? Umimai d'Rabbi Yose
hi?
Who says that's רבי יוסי? Rabbi Yose? דילמא רבי יהודה היא? Dilma
Rabbi Yehuda hi? Maybe it's even רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. דאמר גבי
קריאת שמע נמי בדיעבד אין לכתחילה לא. De'amar gabi Kriat Shema nami
be-di'avad in lechatchila lo. How do you understand רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
when he says it's okay if you didn't hear? Is it בדיעבד,
be-di'avad, you had post facto, but you're supposed to hear? And לכתחילה
lechatchila he would demand it, or he doesn't even need it לכתחילה?
lechatchila? So the גמרא Gemara says maybe he also demands it לכתחילה.
lechatchila. And if he demands it לכתחילה, lechatchila, so a deaf person
shouldn't take תרומה, Truma, get somebody else to take תרומה. Truma. That's
not the idea. By שמע, nobody else can say your שמע, but
by תרומה Truma somebody else can do it. And maybe רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda would demand that.
Does that mean somebody else will take his תרומה? Truma?
Yeah, you could
have you could point someone beforehand.
Well, you can't be יוצא שומע כעונה, yotzei shomea ke-oneh, and somebody
else can't make the ברכה if you're if they're not taking the
תרומה. Truma. So you would have to get appoint somebody else to
take your תרומה. Truma. So that's the question: does רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda demand לכתחילה lechatchila as well that you hear?
Okay, תא ד— ta de— דקתני הקורא, diketani ha-korei, one who says
if you, if you did say the שמע without hearing, בדיעבד bedieved
only post facto, לכתחילה le-chatchilah no, not at the outset. אמרי Amri
no. האי דקתני הקורא, hai diketani ha-korei, that's to say that if
you did it, להודיע כוחו דרבי יוסי, le-hodia kocho de-Rabbi Yossi, to
teach you the strength of רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yossi, דאמר בדיעבד נמי
לא, de-amar bedieved nami lo, that רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi says even
post facto you didn't, דאי רבי יהודה de-ee Rabbi Yehuda because really
if it was what would come to רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, אפילו
לכתחילה נמי יצא. afillu le-chatchilah nami yatza. Okay, maybe רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda allows it לכתחילה. le-chatchilah. So we don't know. We know רבי
יוסי Rabbi Yossi says post facto you're not, but we don't know
רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. Does he say לכתחילה le-chatchilah you're supposed to
be able to hear yourself or not? So let's just read a
little bit more and then we'll end this for today.
גמרא says like this: במאי אוקימתא? bemai ukimta? כרבי יוסי. ke-Rabbi Yossi.
So you're trying to say it's only רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi who's
got the problem. והא דתניא, ve-ha detanya, that which we taught in
the ברייתא, Baraita, לא יברך אדם ברכת המזון בלבו. lo yevarech adam
birchas hamazon belibbo. Do not say ברכת המזון birchas hamazon in your
heart. Now that sounds not like even without mouthing the words. רש"י
though says, and that's a separate question, is הרהור כדיבור דמי, hirhur
ke-dibbur dami, is thinking sometimes enough? But for now we won't get
into that and we will assume it means that you actually mouth
the words but you weren't able to hear it. ואם בירך יצא,
ve-im berach yatza, but בדיעבד bedieved it works. So there you see
לכתחילה le-chatchilah you're supposed to hear it, and בדיעבד bedieved not, assuming
again that the issue was not not just thinking but but even
but you did mouth it but you just didn't hear it. Of
course you could say that the whole problem here was that you
didn't even mouth it. But anyway, I get it. So the גמרא
says who's that going like? לא רבי יוסי ולא רבי יהודה. lo
Rabbi Yossi ve-lo Rabbi Yehuda. According to the way you set it
up there's no middle position. It's either it doesn't work בדיעבד bedieved
or it's allowed לכתחילה. le-chatchilah. Here we have a position, don't do
it לכתחילה, le-chatchilah, it works בדיעבד. bedieved. דאי רבי יהודה, de-ee Rabbi
Yehuda, according to you רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says, האמר לכתחילה נמי
יצא, ha-amar le-chatchilah nami yatza, it works even לכתחילה. le-chatchilah. ואי רבי
יוסי, ve-ee Rabbi Yossi, and if it's רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yossi, בדיעבד
נמי לא, bedieved nami lo, doesn't even work בדיעבד. bedieved.
So how do you have this middle position? Don't do it לכתחילה,
le-chatchilah, you can do it בדיעבד. bedieved. So the גמרא says back,
אלא מאי? ella mai? רבי יהודה? Rabbi Yehuda? בדיעבד אין לכתחילה לא?
bedieved in le-chatchilah lo? So what do you want to say? You
want to say that רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda is a middle position:
don't do it לכתחילה, le-chatchilah, it's okay בדיעבד. bedieved. And that's this
idea of ברכת המזון birchas hamazon that we just quoted. But I'm
going to give you a case that it's clear לכתחילה le-chatchilah it's
fine. והא דתניא, ve-ha detanya, we taught in the ברייתא, Baraita, רבי
יהודה בריה דרבי שמעון בן פזי, Rabbi Yehuda bereih de-Rabbi Shimon ben
Pazi, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda the son of רבי שמעון בן פזי
Rabbi Shimon ben Pazi says, חרש המדבר ואינו שומע, cheresh ha-medabber ve-eino
shomea, if somebody is cannot hear but can speak, תורם לכתחילה, torem
le-chatchilah, can do it even לכתחילה. le-chatchilah. So clearly we have a
לכתחילה le-chatchilah position. So what the גמרא has now done is it's
laid out three positions. רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi says בדיעבד bedieved it
does not work. We have this position here about about in the
name of רבי שמעון בר פזי Rabbi Sim bar ben Pazi that
even לכתחילה le-chatchilah you can do it by תרומה. terumah. And then
we have the ברכת המזון birchas hamazon position that says לכתחילה le-chatchilah
no, בדיעבד bedieved yes. Okay, so we have all three positions. So
the question is which one is the רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda position?
Of ברכת המזון, birchas hamazon, שמע, and תרומה, terumah, how are they
all the same?
Right, and we're assuming that that's all the same and it can
all be compared. So the גמרא says who is that? לא רבי
יהודה ולא רבי יוסי. lo Rabbi Yehuda ve-lo Rabbi Yossi. אי רבי
יהודה, ee Rabbi Yehuda, if you're saying רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda is
only a middle position, האמר בדיעבד אין לכתחילה לא, ha-amar bedieved in
le-chatchilah lo, he only allows it בדיעבד. bedieved. And here we're having
a position that says even לכתחילה le-chatchilah you can take the תרומה.
terumah. אי רבי יוסי, ee Rabbi Yossi, if it's רבי יוסי, Rabbi
Yossi, האמר בדיעבד נמי לא, ha-amar bedieved nami lo, not even בדיעבד.
bedieved. So basically you cannot say, we have three positions and two
people, so which how are you going to make it work? So
the גמרא says לעולם רבי יהודה. le-olam Rabbi Yehuda. Really I could
say it's רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda ואפילו לכתחילה נמי, ve-afillu le-chatchilah nami,
and רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda would allow it לכתחילה. le-chatchilah.
And
how do I deal with the middle position that says by ברכת
המזון birchas hamazon don't do it לכתחילה? le-chatchilah? הא דידיה הא דרביה.
ha didey ha drabbey. Maybe one is his own position, his own
position he would say לכתחילה le-chatchilah you can do it. The middle
position of ברכת המזון, birchas hamazon, that's his רב'ס Rebbi's position. דתניא,
we taught in the משנה or the ברייתא, Baraita רבי יהודה אומר
משום רבי אלעזר בן עזריה. Rabbi Yehuda omer mishum Rabbi Elazar ben
Azarya. He says in the name of his רב, רבי אלעזר בן
עזריה, Rabbi Elazar ben Azarya, הקורא את שמע צריך שישמיע לאוזנו, ha-korei
et shema tzarich she-yashmia le-ozno, that when you say שמע לכתחילה le-chatchilah
you have to be able to hear what you're saying, שנאמר שמע
ישראל ה' אלהינו ה' אחד. she-ne'emar shema yisrael hashem elokeinu hashem echad.
So what we have said before I read the end of the
ברייתא Baraita is the following: we have a clear ברייתא Baraita that
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda in the name of his רב says לכתחילה
le-chatchilah you have to hear, צריך. tzarich. צריך tzarich means you're supposed
to, but it doesn't mean it won't work if you don't. So
we have him saying in the name of his רב לכתחילה le-chatchilah
you have to say it, בדיעבד bedieved you don't. That's the middle
position. We have other opinions out there that say even לכתחילה le-chatchilah
you don't, like the position of תרומה. terumah. So the way we're
going to resolve it is we're going to say okay, רבי יוסי
Rabbi Yossi says it doesn't work even בדיעבד. bedieved. רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda himself says it works even לכתחילה le-chatchilah by שמע, by ברכת
המזון, birchas hamazon, by תרומה terumah etc. How about the position that
it only works בדיעבד bedieved like the like the ברכת המזון birchas
hamazon ברייתא that we quoted? That's רבי יהודה'ס Rabbi Yehuda's רב. That's
what we see here that רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda in the name
of his רב says לכתחילה le-chatchilah you're supposed to, בדיעבד bedieved not.
And we'll just end this right now where the
גמרא says אמר רבי מאיר, amar Rabbi Meir, where is רבי מאיר?
Rabbi Meir? שנאמר שמע ישראל ה' אלהינו ה' אחד. she-ne'emar shema yisrael
hashem elokeinu hashem echad. אמר לו רבי מאיר, amar lo Rabbi Meir,
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir said back, הרי הוא אומר אשר אנכי מצוך
היום על לבבך, harei hu omer asher anochi metzavecha hayom al levavecha,
on your heart, which we discussed before about the requirements of intention,
אחר כוונת הלב הן הן הדברים, achar kavanat halev hen hen hadevarim,
that you don't even have to make it heard, it's all about
what you're thinking. Again, maybe you don’t even have
to mutter the words, maybe just thinking is enough. And the גמרא
ends by saying, השתא דאתית להכא, hashta de-atit le-hacha, now that we’ve
introduced רבי מאיר, Rebbi Meir, that רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir says you
don’t have to hear it, you can just think it, אפילו תימא
רבי יהודה כרביה סבירא ליה, afillu teima Rebbi Yehuda kerabbeih sevira lei,
maybe you’re right, maybe רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda is the middle position
who says לכתחילה. lechatchila. What about the position that it’s only בדיעבד?
bedi'avad? What about the position that לכתחילה lechatchila it’s okay? ולא קשיא
הא רבי מאיר הא רבי יהודה. velo kashya ha Rebbi Meir ha
Rebbi Yehuda. רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir is the one that says that
לכתחילה lechatchila it’s okay. So what we have here is, just to
sum up, we have three positions. רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yosi, it doesn’t
even work בדיעבד. bedi'avad. Two positions about other positions. One is לכתחילה,
lechatchila, even לכתחילה lechatchila it’s okay, and the other is no, לכתחילה
lechatchila you have to hear, בדיעבד bedi'avad not. How do we explain
those two positions? So we don’t know. Maybe רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
says one and his רבי says the other, or maybe, more simply,
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says it works בדיעבד, bedi'avad, but רבי מאיר
Rebbi Meir says even לכתחילה. lechatchila. And then the question becomes, is
that לכתחילה lechatchila even without moving your lips? Because we’ve had now
two positions that said בליבא, beliba, אחר כוונת הלב. achar kavanat halev.
Maybe it’s so much that you don’t even have to articulate, maybe
just thinking, maybe הרהור כדיבור דמי. hirhur kedibbur dami. But
certainly לכתחילה lechatchila it’s okay, that is the position of רבי מאיר.
Rebbi Meir. And the open issue is, is this unique to שמע?
We’ve now studied many different categories, or maybe there’s a difference between
the categories. So we will continue with this discussion tomorrow. So
I guess what are we going to do? We’re going to do
one more to catch, fully catch up.